<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Alessandro Baffa</title>
    <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Alessandro Baffa</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 12:23:42 +0900</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>日本語勉強 - Personal recommendations for Japanese learners</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/japanese-learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 12:23:42 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/japanese-learning/</guid>
      <description>This is a list of resources that I&amp;rsquo;m finding exceptional for my Japanese studies. I&amp;rsquo;m at a JLPT N4 level at the moment.
Reading Read, read, read. You need to read until you destroy the visual and mental barrier of kanji. Until you don&amp;rsquo;t reach that point, your eyes will naturally tend to skip the entire content to pass to something else you can read without effort. So, force your mind to stop and read it all until your brain will stop making antibodies for kanji.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On NFT (2 part)</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/on-nft-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2021 08:17:31 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/on-nft-2/</guid>
      <description>Non-Fungible Tokens (NFT) are interesting, but there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of confusion about the concept of ownership. If you buy a NFT, you are only buying the ownership of a pointer to a metadata (audio, video, etc..) stored somewhere (more likely a centralized server, only some use IPFS). But this pointed metadata can be counterfeit (e.g. the NFT could be a screenshot. And this happening often now), so you still need an additional way to prove the actual asset is legit, the &amp;ldquo;oracle problem&amp;rdquo;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On NFTs..</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/on-nfts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 17:45:41 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/on-nfts/</guid>
      <description>Non-Fungible Tokens (#NFTs) is a very wide topic and I do not want to go in details here, so I just suggest a couple of links:
 The Non-Fungible Tokens Bible by OpenSea : it contains everything you need to know about NFTs. A Beginner&amp;rsquo;s Guide to NFTs: it contains an interesting panorama of all types of existing NFTs (i.e.: NFT is not only art or gaming. This blog is using a NFT as domain name: alebaffa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Decentralized Blog</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/decentralized-blog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 15:35:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/decentralized-blog/</guid>
      <description>This blog is now hosted on IPFS, the Interplanetary Filesystem.
I&amp;rsquo;m using Hugo and Fleek.co to automatically build and deploy the static files on IPFS.
There are three ways to see this page. The first is to use a standard browser (Chrome, Firefox..etc) with extensions such as IPFS Companion that uses a IPNS gateway set up by default (or you can install IPFS and run a node locally), or the Metamask plugin, and when you type http://alebaffa.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unit testing a static custom logger in Spring Boot and log4j2</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/spring-boot-custom-logger-log4j2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Mar 2018 23:02:43 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/spring-boot-custom-logger-log4j2/</guid>
      <description>Last time I wrote a post about how to unit test a custom logger with log4j2. Today I migrated another custom logger from log4j 1.x to log4j 2.x, but this time it was encapsulated in a Spring Boot component as a static class attribute.
Custom logger You have a simple custom logger
public class SimpleCustomLogger { private final ExtendedLoggerWrapper log; private SimpleCustomLogger(final Logger log) { this.log = new ExtendedLoggerWrapper((AbstractLogger) log, log.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unit testing a custom logger in log4j2</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/unit-testing-custom-logger-log4j2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Mar 2018 13:55:46 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/unit-testing-custom-logger-log4j2/</guid>
      <description>In this period I&amp;rsquo;m upgrading a Spring Boot project from 1.3 &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 1.5 &amp;ndash;&amp;gt; 2.0. One of the steps is to get rid of log4j 1.x.
In the project there is custom logger, but unfortunately its unit test with log4j2 is no more working and we receive the following error:
 mockito wanted but not invoked, Actually there were zero interactions with this mock
 Basically this exact same error in Stackoverflow.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Debug a Java Spring Boot application in Docker from IntelliJ</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/debug-java-docker-compose-intellij/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2018 23:19:11 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/debug-java-docker-compose-intellij/</guid>
      <description>You have a Java Spring Boot application built with Gradle in a Docker container and you need to debug it from your favorite IDE on your host machine (IntelliJ).
You can do it by attaching the remote debugger in IntelliJ to your Java application running in Docker.
Steps Open port :5005 in the container In this example the Java container is created using docker-compose. All you need to do here is to open the port :5005:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jupyter: the easiest way to import code from another notebook</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/jupyter-import-notebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2018 19:57:31 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/jupyter-import-notebook/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I published a post about how to create a module in jupyter.
There is another way to quickly import the code from another notebook. Say you are working in your_notebook.ipynb and you need a Python class class Hello(): from another_notebook.ipynb. To import it you just need to do the following:
# in your_notebook.ipynb do %run another_notebook.ipynb hello = Hello() Voila, with %run you access the code from the other notebook.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create modules in Jupyter notebooks</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/create_modules_in_jupyter_notebooks/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2018 21:38:37 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/create_modules_in_jupyter_notebooks/</guid>
      <description>In my current attempt to improve the development experience of my team, I am trying to introduce Jupyter notebooks to share knowledge about some data analysis scripts developed over the last years. I can copy paste the code into a notebook, run the single cells to show the result below the code, export the notebook as markdown and push it to Bitbucket: voila, documentation.
Though, a disadvantage of Jupyter notebooks over Python scripts is that they cannot be linked to each other.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Journey towards Continuous Integration - Part 1</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/road-towards-ci-part-one/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2018 21:06:57 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/road-towards-ci-part-one/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I am going to write a set of posts that describe what I quickly talked about in the last Docker Tokyo Meetup. Though, this is not going to be focused on Docker only, but rather on all the challenges I found/I&amp;rsquo;m finding trying to set up the Continuous Integration for my team&amp;rsquo;s project. Nevertheless, Docker played/is playing an important role and it has revealed some interesting things about the quality of the project itself, which I&amp;rsquo;m trying to fix.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving the development experience: Jupyter for Elasticsearch</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/elastic-search-jupyter/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2018 19:59:13 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/elastic-search-jupyter/</guid>
      <description>I have been asked to extract data from Elasticsearch and I had no clue of what kind of data were stored inside of it. Moreover, there was a lack of documentation and the only thing that could help me were some old Python scripts written by an old colleague.
Fortunately, Python is pretty damn good when it comes to readability.
So, because I am working to improve the development experience of my team and I am messing around with Jupyter, I thought I could create a Jupyter notebook with a super simple Elasticsearch client in Python 3 that supports a connection with a proxy (vital, if working in a company).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My current learning journey</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/my-last-seven-months/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/my-last-seven-months/</guid>
      <description>I started my journey at Rakuten in June 2017 and, more precisely, I am Full Stack Engineer working for Rakuten Magazine. It&amp;rsquo;s a pretty new Web project, so it&amp;rsquo;s not big and we are very few people: 4 guys focused on Web and API (myself included), and 3 guys on Android/iOS.
First huge difference from my previous job: here I can put my hands on literally everything. We have a total freedom to choose what technology stack to use, if it&amp;rsquo;s reasonable and well argumented.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Changing Everything. Again.</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/new-chapter-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Feb 2017 08:03:16 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/new-chapter-of-life/</guid>
      <description>After 7 years spent in France I am officially moving to Tokyo, Japan, end of May 2017. I am finally going to join my wife, Sarah, after almost 5 years of long and hard distant relationship.
Now, before to start with the burocracy madness and to move/sell/close/sign things, I am sitting here at home, in the first weekend after having resigned from my current company, trying to think about how many things I learned over the last 7 years.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Back from SoCraTes France 2016</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/socrates-france/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2016 12:29:46 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/socrates-france/</guid>
      <description>My second time in a Software Craftsmanship and Testing (SoCraTes) conference and, as always, it has been an awesome experience.
The self-made agenda SoCraTes is a non-conference, which means that there’s no predefined agenda, but instead it is created every day by the participants (the image above is the agenda of day 2). Everybody is more than welcome to propose sessions. They can be presentation of something you know, or open discussion about a topic you are curious about, or more simply a session where you want to learn something and you are looking for someone more experienced to help you.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Global Day of Coderetreat 2016, Sophia Antipolis, France</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/global-day-of-coderetreat/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Oct 2016 12:29:46 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/global-day-of-coderetreat/</guid>
      <description>We did it! The Global Day of Coderetreat in Sophia Antipolis has been a great success! My first coderetreat ever, and I played the role of the organizer and facilitator. It’s an event that I started to organize in August and I have been lucky to find the support of the University of Nice-Sophia Antipolis and my company, Amadeus IT Group. In the organization of all this I have been hugely helped by other people who have been facilitators with me (we were 3 facilitators, 1 host and 2 facilitators/helpers).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dependency Injection VS Extract and Override Factory Method</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/racing-car-kata-refactoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2016 21:17:23 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/racing-car-kata-refactoring/</guid>
      <description>The TextConverter exercise (in the Racing Car kata suite) is a very interesting exercise for refactoring legacy code. As I am reading Working Effectively with Legacy Code I found two ways of solving it.
Refactoring can only be done safely with unit tests and so I did, rigourously in TDD. Though, in this blog post I am not going to show you all the testing process, but only the two ways of decoupling the dependency.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Community of Professionals - SoCraTes UK</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/socrates-uk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Jun 2016 21:28:33 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/socrates-uk/</guid>
      <description>A couple of weeks ago I participated for the first time to a SoCraTes event, one of the Software Craftsmanship international gatherings. SoCraTes (Software Craftsmanship and Testing) is an self-organized conference where the people from the international Software Craftsmanship Community meet and spend 3 days organizing themselves activities and talks around everything related to software craftsmanship: from the technical to the human aspects of it. There are few events of this kind every year (Italy, France, Germany, Belgium, Switzerland, Romania, Finland, Canaries) and I participated to the one in UK.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amarcord - Old posts from 2011 (ITA/ENG)</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/amarcord-2011/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Feb 2011 10:37:06 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/amarcord-2011/</guid>
      <description>&amp;raquo; Non ci penso un attimo: faccio benzina in Svizzera.  Infatti, la carta regionale dei servizi è ormai un documento che hanno tutti, ma non tutti hanno il pin, cioè il codice per attivarla e c’è chi non s’è accorto che è scaduta e ne deve chiedere una nuova. Dove: alla Asl, ai Comuni abilitati o a Spazio Regione, lo sportello dei cittadini presso il Pirellino, in via Benzi – Viale Varese a Como.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amarcord - Old posts from 2010 (ITA)</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/amarcord-2010/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2010 10:07:16 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/amarcord-2010/</guid>
      <description>September 2010 &amp;raquo;&amp;gt; Global Minds L’esperienza di vita all’estero è qualcosa che non smetterò mai di consigliare a tutti. E’ un’esperienza da prendere al volo, qualcosa per cui vale la pena mollare tutto e tutti e partire senza troppe riflessioni e calcoli. Di lati negativi ce ne sono, ma di lati positivi ce ne sono altrettanti e alcuni che sto scoprendo solo ora. E’ proprio vero che l’esperienza internazionale ti apre la mente, fa crollare alcune barriere che sono puramente psicologiche e che non ci accorgiamo di avere.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amarcord - Old posts from 2009 (ITA)</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/amarcord-2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Feb 2009 10:05:04 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/amarcord-2009/</guid>
      <description>February &amp;raquo; Mail: disaster recovery Mi sto dando al backup delle email. Il blackout dell’altro giorno di Gmail mi ha messo abbastanza ansia.
Ho provato Gmail offline con Google Gears e, nonostante sia abbastanza comodo, mi da problemi con Firefox che continua a crashare quando cambio qualche impostazione (Gears tenta di sincronizzare e crolla tutto). Ho provato anche gmail-backup, proprio come backup grezzo e classico giusto per avere fisicamente salvate le mail da qualche parte, e lo trovo utile, ma come sistema da ultima spiaggia: semmai Gmail morirà, comunque avreste tutti i file delle mail salvate nel vostro pc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amarcord - Old posts from 2008 (ITA)</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/amarcord-2008/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Feb 2008 09:42:00 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/amarcord-2008/</guid>
      <description>Posts from 2008 January &amp;raquo;&amp;gt; 100 di questi anni!! 7 anni fa veniva messa online Wikipedia, la prima enciclopedia online mantenuta dagli utenti in modo collaborativo e volontario. Dopo 7 anni è diventato uno dei 10 siti più visitati al mondo con circa 60 MILIONI di visite al giorno e tradotto in 250 lingue diverse All’inizio del 2008, Wikipedia contiene in totale più di 9,35 milioni di voci, 31 milioni di pagine, con 419 milioni di modifiche alle pagine e 10,25 milioni di utenti registrati.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Amarcord - Old posts from 2007 (ITA)</title>
      <link>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/amarcord-2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 08 Sep 2007 08:49:18 +0900</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://alebaffa.eth.link/post/amarcord-2007/</guid>
      <description>Posts from 2007 September &amp;raquo;&amp;gt; Crea il tuo avatar personalizzato doppelme è un’applicazione online che permette di creare il proprio avatar personalizzato in pochi e semplici passi. Le (non troppe, ma essenziali) opzioni vanno dalla scelta della capigliatura, al colore degli occhi, le scarpe, la barba..e alla fine potete creare un avatar che vi rappresenta (come il mio da oggi in alto a destra ;-) ).
&amp;raquo;&amp;gt; Quando Sono Le Aziende Ad Infrangere Il Diritto D’Ingegno Degli Utenti Alquanto singolare quanto accaduto ultimamente sui siti del gruppo L’Espresso.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>